Okay so
today's דף daf is פ"ח Peh-Ches and we pick up at the
bottom of פ"ז עמוד ב' Peh-Zayin Amud Beis and we were having
some fascinating discussion אגדתא aggadata but the questions about why we went
into גלות. galus. One issue is to pick up גרים gerim and
the other is here about why specifically בבל Bavel then it turned
to a discussion
and it was that that's going back to our place of origin
was one answer. The other was it was like a sense of
שאול sheol the underworld the depths and so on. Also because בבל
Bavel was seen as more hospitable to Jews than living in Israel
under Roman rule. So now the גמרא Gemara says עולא אמר Ulla
amar last four words on פ"ז עמוד ב'. Peh-Zayin Amud Beis. עולא
אמר כדי שיאכלו תמרים ויעסקו בתורה Ulla amar kedei she-yochlu temarim ve-ya'asku
ba-Torah in order that they should eat dates and learn תורה Torah
because בבל Bavel apparently it's funny because you think like Israel you
know יריחו Yericho is עיר התמרים Ir Ha-Temarim but apparently dates were
very plentiful in בבל Bavel so you know food was plentiful it
was a it was easy to make a living and therefore
that it's sort of like taking the idea that they couldn't deal
with the hardship of living under Roman rule but rather more about
the positive than about the negative not about fleeing from persecution but
actually it was very easy to earn a living and therefore they
would be free to learn תורה. Torah.
The only reason why there are date trees now in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael is because the early Zionists stole four trees from Iraq
and...
Okay but I mean יריחו Yericho is עיר התמרים Ir Ha-Temarim already
in תנ"ך Tanakh so I think there were date trees in them...
Something happened in
between.
Right ארץ זבת חלב ודבש.
Eretz zavat chalav u-dvash.
Right exactly. Exactly. Alright. עולא Ulla so now עולא Ulla who originated
in Israel איקלע לפומבדיתא ikla le-Pumbedita was visiting פומבדיתא. Pumbedita. קריבו ליה
טנא דתמרי Kareivu lei tana de-tamrei they brought him like a basket
full of dates. So אמר להו amar lehu he says to the
people כמה כי הני בזוזא? kama ki hani be-zuza? How much of
these for a זוזא zuza which is you know a dollar a
quarter whatever. אמרו
ליה amru lei תלתא בזוזא telasa be-zuza three for a זוזא zuza
presumably three baskets I think or three... whatever. Anyway very cheap. אמר
amar מלא טנא דובשא בזוזא mala tana de-duvsha be-zuza a basket full
of honey right like Rivka was saying דבש dvash is דבש תמרים
dvash temarim a basket full of honey for a זוזא zuza ובבלאי
לא עסקי באורייתא u-Vavlayei lo aski be-Oraisa and Babylonians can't learn תורה
Torah things are so cheap here! בליליא Be-leilya at night צערוהו tza'aruhu
all of those dates gave him a stomach ache. He went
overboard. אמר amar מלא טנא סמא דמותא בזוזא mala tana samma de-mosa
be-zuza a basket full of poison for a זוזא zuza בבבל be-Bavel
בבלאי
עסקי באורייתא Vavlayei aski be-Oraisa look look how they learn תורה Torah
even with this! Right that famous חסידית Chassidic story right? You know
the story about the ליטוואק Litvak and the חסיד Chassid that are
walking by... Exactly! And the בעל עגלה ba'al agala changing the wheel.
And the ליטוואק Litvak says look at that his hand you know
filthy his hands and it's disgusting and he's דאווענינג. davening. And the
חסיד Chassid looks up and says ריבונו של עולם Ribono Shel Olam
your people even when their hands are filthy in the mud they're
still thinking about you and they're still דאווענינג. davening. What? It's a
ברדיטשעווער Berditchever story. ברדיטשעווער Berditchever story okay.
So anyway I guess it's two versions here. But of course the
point being you know what I think we can take this to
heart as living in a good standard of living here in America
is just because you have a good standard of living doesn't always
mean that you spend more time learning. Sometimes it's a you know
makes it it's it makes it too easy to to just take
life easy.
And it's not always so good for your health.
And it's not always... very good excellent excellent well said. Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. All
right.
Okay. Where are we? Okay. ואמר רבי אלעזר Ve-amar Rabbi Elazar מאי
דכתיב mai de-ksiv what's meant by the פסוק pasuk והלכו עמים רבים
ואמרו לכו ונעלה אל הר ה' אל בית אלהי יעקב Ve-halchu amim
rabim ve-amru lechu ve-na'aleh el har Hashem el beis Elokei Ya'akov and
the nations will say because this also is evoking right the you
know the idea that we alluded to before about the regathering of
exiles and coming back from the פסוקים pesukim in עמוס. Amos. So
what is meant that it says many nations will come and say
let us go up to the mountain of God to the house
of the God of יעקב? Ya'akov? אלהי יצחק לא? Elokei Yitzchak lo?
אלהי... I'm sorry. אלהי יעקב Ya'akov ולא אלהי אברהם Avraham ויצחק? What
only the God of יעקב Ya'akov and not of אברהם Avraham and
יצחק? Yitzchak? אלא Ella yeah but here's what it means. לא כאברהם
שכתוב בו הר. Lo ke-Avraham she-kasuv bo har. By אברהם Avraham what
does how does it refer to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash as
a mountain? שנאמר אשר יאמר היום בהר ה' יראה She-ne'emar asher ye'amer
hayom be-har Hashem yeira'eh God will appear in the mountain. ולא כיצחק
שנאמר בו שדה Ve-lo ke-Yitzchak she-ne'emar bo sadeh not by יצחק Yitzchak
where his encounter with God was in the field. שנאמר ויצא יצחק
לשוח בשדה. She-ne'emar vayeitzei Yitzchak lasu'ach ba-sadeh. אלא כיעקב שקראו בית Ella
ke-Ya'akov she-karo bayis but it's like יעקב who called it a house.
שנאמר ויקרא שם המקום ההוא בית אל. She-ne'emar vayikra shem ha-makom ha-hu
Beis El. Now what's the significance of calling it a house? Well
you know let's finish the two dots and then I'll go back
because this will tie into the פסוק pasuk we had before by
הושע. Hoshea. אמר רבי יוחנן גדול קיבוץ גלויות כיום שנבראו בו שמים
וארץ. Amar Rabbi Yochanan gadol kibbutz galuyos ke-yom she-nivreu vo shamayim va-aretz.
The day of the gathering of the exiles is as great as
the day the heaven and earth was created, it's a new creation
of the world, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, ונקבצו בני יהודה ובני ישראל יחדיו ושמו
להם ראש אחד ועלו מן הארץ כי גדול יום יזרעאל, V'nikbetzu bnei
Yehuda u-vnei Yisrael yachdav v'samu lahem rosh echad v'alu min ha-aretz ki
gadol yom Yizre'el, again evoking like the, the, the sin of יזרעאל
Yizre'el and here getting not exactly clear what יזרעאל Yizre'el means in
this context, the planting, the gathering of ישראל, Yisrael, רש"י Rashi suggests,
but anyway also this sense that, you know, here the re-gathering of
the exiles are בני יהודה ובני ישראל bnei Yehuda bnei Yisrael as
opposed to the prophecy that was that they would be sent into
exile. So it's כי גדול יום יזרעאל ki gadol yom Yizre'el וכתיב
ויהי ערב ויהי בוקר יום אחד. v'chtiv v'yehi erev v'yehi voker yom
echad. The emphasis on day, it's like it's a new day of
creation, a new world of creation. That doesn't happen often though. Right,
I know. So what are you going to do? Anyway, that cuts
off the discussion of, that wraps up the discussion we had before
from הושע Hoshea and sort of gives it a nice closure. I
want to say one word about the idea of, I very much
like this אגדתא aggadata about יעקב שקראו בית. Yaakov she-kera'o bayit. If
you look at רש"י, Rashi, what's the significance of בית? bayit? רש"י
Rashi just says מקום מיושב, makom meyushav, settled. All right, not exactly
clear what's so significant. But I think what it's getting to is,
you know, that, that it's like the one aspect and way of
the חידוש chiddush of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is this sense
that you take an idea of an infinite God and you actually,
you know, understand that in a way, if God is everywhere, it
can be hard to get a sense of a particular location and
presence, and you know, if he's everywhere he could also be nowhere.
So you have אברהם and יצחק, Yitzchak, you see God on the
mountains, you know, you see God in the fields, in the way
also what the תורה Torah speaks about, at the beginning, you know,
where it says, you know, with the non-Jews, you know, that they
have all of their, of their altars, על ההרים הגבוהים ועל הגבעות
ותחת כל עץ רענן, al he-harim ha-gevohim v'al ha-gevaot v'tachat kol etz
ra'anan, right? So, you know, obviously that was a pagan religion, but
obviously part of the paradox is, you know, as שלמה המלך Shlomo
HaMelech says, הנה השמים ושמי השמים לא יכלכלוך ואף כי הבית הזה
אשר בניתי. hinei ha-shamayim u-shmei ha-shamayim lo yechalchelucha v'af ki ha-bayit ha-zeh
asher baniti. How do you have this idea of an infinite God
but that's the, you know, having a more local, focused presence in
a particular place? That's the חידוש chiddush of the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, right? Which it says, you know, it says, השם אמר לשכון
בערפל. Hashem amar lishkon ba-arafel. Right, you're, you know, what you have
done is you have somehow allowed your presence to be felt more
intensely at one place. So one aspect of the בית bayit and
all of the nations will come, you know, is the sense that,
again, you know, both it's the belief of an infinite God, but
also that sense that there can be one place that focuses everybody's
energies and prayers and tensions, and that becomes a central place of
worship and that, you know, does more for the unified idea of
God. I mean, again, it's a little bit ironic, because some of
us might think the opposite, that the more you have a particular
temple, you know, the less of a universal God that is. But
I think that the, you know, I think that in the תורה,
Torah, if, you know, A, if God is everywhere, it's hard to
relate. You need something more specific and concrete to give you a
means to relate. And also if God is everywhere, it could lead
to the idea of the multiplicity of gods, whereas the whole idea
of דברים Devarim is that there's one central location, one God, one
place of worship, one central location, and so on. So that's one
aspect, I think, about the idea of בית. bayit. The other thing
that I would say, and is, you know, that the sense that
a בית bayit also is a human construction as opposed to a
הר har and a שדה. sadeh. And the whole idea is, you
know, ועשו לי מקדש ושכנתי בתוכם, v'asu li mikdash v'shachanti b'tocham, that
you actually do the work of creating that space, and that's, and
that then allows God's presence to reside in it. I don't know
who the first person who was to make this point, it's not
me, but, you know, הר סיני, Har Sinai, which is where God's
presence was most felt, right, God came down from heaven, whatever that
means, has no lasting קדושה, kedusha, right? The, the, the place of
the מקדש Mikdash has lasting קדושה. kedusha. So the things that we
sort of build and create and construct and when we create that
space, you know, that lets God in more meaningful ways, way inhabit
that space, and in a way that's really of a lasting and
of an eternal nature. So, I think that the, you know, there's
a lot here, I think, in the idea of the sense of
בית bayit as opposed to experiencing God in nature, which I should
by the way say, I love דאווענינג davening outdoors. I feel much
more connected when I דאווען daven outdoors. So all of that being
said, there's a power of encountering God in nature as well, but
I think this is also dealing with the power of a single
location, of a focused location, and the idea of working to construct
that space in which God will inhabit. Okay, yes, and I think
רש"י Rashi says, and שלמה Shlomo has articulated that theology already. Right,
right, like so, it's like overt. Yeah, yeah, I know, I mean,
if you just read it a little bit closely, you know, it's,
it's exactly dealing with this paradox, exactly. And it's in terms of
ההפטורה ha-Haftorah which is to tie up what we were saying before.
Yep, yeah, about the, exactly. All right, so now, so now we
move on, but don't worry, we're having such a good time. we're
not giving up on our what do you call it, on our
אגדתא, aggadata, there's more to come. Okay, but we have a little,
we have a little הלכתי halachic digression. So back to the משנה.
mishna. יתום ששחטו עליו אפוטרופסיו. Yatom sheshachatu alav apitropsav. So you have
this orphan that the caretakers... whatever, guardian, executor, slaughtered a קרבן פסח,
korban Pesach, so there are two different ones, and he gets to
eat whichever one he chooses. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה
יש ברירה, shema mina yesh breira, just like the discussion about the
woman and her husband, it sounds like יש ברירה, yesh breira, that
he can decide after it was slaughtered and it'll determine what do
you call it, and yeah that'll allow to determine retroactively who it
was slaughtered for. So אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira שה לבית
seh l'vayit מכל מקום. mikol makom. So it says שה לבית אבות
שה לבית seh l'veit avot seh l'vayit regardless. What that means is
presumably פשט pshat of this גמרא, Gemara, we'll read a little bit
more and then I'll tell you about a different גמרא Gemara in
נדרים, Nedarim, but part of פשט pshat of this גמרא Gemara is
that there's an idea of a household. You know, we sort of
have abstracted, and again, this sort of goes to the interesting interplay
between חבורה chaburah and בית. bayit. Right, the תורה Torah speaks about
don't take it out of the house, שה לבית אבות שה לבית.
seh l'veit avot seh l'vayit. We abstracted to this idea of חבורה.
chaburah. And then we had an interesting discussion, how much does בית
bayit still play a role once we have this concept of חבורה?
chaburah? So similarly within that idea of חבורה chaburah is also not
just the physical location but who's members of it. In the תורה,
Torah, it's the members of the household, right? Whereas we, anybody you
want to be members, doesn't have to be with members of your
household. How much does the idea of household still a dominant concept,
you know, even after that? So the גמרא Gemara interestingly rejected that
or not suggested this by husband and wife. You know, wife was
seen as independent for you to choose her own grouping. The only
issue about whether the husband slaughtered and worked for her was whether
she implicitly would have wanted it or not. Whereas by the children,
and here it's even by orphans, which is interesting, that you could
have this idea of בית bayit transferring. But the גמרא Gemara in
נדרים Nedarim uses this by just speaking about a, we're going to
back quote a minute, also about a father slaughtering for his children
without soliciting their input, there, or maybe even against their will, tough
luck on the father, you're the kids, this is what we're doing
for our household. The idea of household dictates, is a unit even
without buying in. For minor kids? For minor kids, right, and for
slaves. Not for wife, not for adult kids. But again, it's like
two models: physical house versus חבורה, chaburah, members of the household as
an objective reality and then also people that buy in. So the
גמרא's Gemara's answer here is that you know what, the kids didn't
buy in, but you don't need them to buy in, they're part
of the household. Now of course the funny thing is, a, that
it's not a biological household, you have it as sort of a
quasi-guardianship, you have אפוטרופוס. apitropos. And number two is that you've got
competitors, one אפוטרופוס apitropos slaughtered, you know, אפוטרופוס apitropos A slaughtered for
the kid and אפוטרופוס apitropos B slaughtered for the kid. So in
a way, but the point is that he doesn't have to buy
in ahead of time, he really was שייך, shayach, you know, he
was like grouped with both house, with both units. So it was,
so he whichever he can choose presumably even later because it's not
a question of him participating before the שחיטה, shechitah, it's an objective
reality of him being part of those households. Still the funny thing
is though that he's now part of two households and he gets
to choose which one. How old? So presumably he's a minor. That's
normally what the, אפוטרופוס apitropos is always for, right, minors. A minor
is under what age? 12 or 13. Boy, girl? Yeah exactly, exactly.
Okay, so let's take a look. But again, so the idea that
there's an objective idea of household is, you know, makes a lot
of sense. How to deal with it with the case of אפוטרופסין
apitropsin and two אפוטרופסין apitropsin is less clear. So anyway let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. שה לבית, Seh
l'vayit, a sheep for the house. שמא תאמר, Shema tomar, maybe ישחוט
yishchot על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים, al yedei bno u'vito haktanim, a
person can bring, a man can bring for his son and daughter
who are minors. ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים, ve'al yedei avdo u'shifchato
hakna'anim, or his male and female non-Jewish slaves that are considered to
be totally under his control. בין מדעתם בין שלא מדעתם, bein mada'atam
bein shelo mada'atam, whether with their knowledge or not. And as the
גמרא Gemara is going to say later, it's not only that they
weren't asked, but even if they verbally objected and said we don't
want to be part of the household, tough luck. It doesn't, that's
not clear now, but that's what the גמרא Gemara will say. אבל
אינו שוחט על ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים, Aval eino shochet al yedei
bno u'vito hagedolim, he cannot slaughter for his adult children. ועל ידי
עבדו ושפחתו העברים, ve'al yedei avdo u'shifchato ha'ivrim, or his Hebrew slaves,
his Jewish slaves, because those while they are sort of, it's more
like, you know, indentured servitude, but they are not actually his property.
And therefore they are their own, you know, they're under their own
control. ועל ידי אשתו, ve'al yedei ishto, and not his wife, that's
not household, right? The thing that he has total control over are
seen to be children and slaves. אלא מדעתן, Ela mada'atan, those it
has to be with their buy-in. That is, and that's why we
didn't give this answer earlier when we dealt with the issue of
the wife. And כנעני Kna'ani you have to translate as slave and
not as servant? Correct. In the גמרא Gemara there is no question.
that עבד Eved is and שפחה כנעני Shifcha Kena'ani are actual property
owned, like, now, chattel. Of course, the חידוש chiddush of the תורה
Torah is that they're not just property. The חידוש chiddush of the
תורה Torah already before you get to חזל, Chazal, you know, is
that a person kills a slave he's, you know, he can be
put to death even though this was somebody you know that was
otherwise seen as property. So anyway, so there was this ancient Near
Eastern context. Right, the תורה Torah was tremendously revolutionary in recognizing this
person both as a human but did not deny the sort of
the standard institution of slavery of also seeing them as property. Rivka,
yes? I thought since we learned earlier that women are obligated for...
Ah, no, so all of that is coming up whether they're obligated
or not. It sounds like they are, but of course minors aren't
obligated either. So it's a question here about who can they eat
with, not necessarily do they fulfill obligation. Right, there'll be an explicit
discussion coming up about whether women are obligated in the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. That's not necessarily inferable here because it's certainly not true
about minors. Okay, תניא אידך, tanya idach, there's another ברייתא braita very
similar although coming from the other direction. לא ישחוט אדם לא על
ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים, lo yishchot adam lo al yedei b'no u'vito
hagedolim, don't slaughter for your adult children, ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו העברים,
v'al yedei avdo v'shifchato ha'ivrim, or your male and female Jewish slaves,
ועל ידי אשתו, v'al yedei ishto, or for your wife, אלא מדעתן,
ella medatan, except for their knowledge and buy-in. אבל שוחט הוא על
ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים, aval shochet hu al yedei b'no u'vito haktanim,
you can slaughter for your minor children, ועל ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים,
v'al yedei avdo v'shifchato hakna'anim, or for your male and female non-Jewish
slaves, בין מדעתן בין שלא מדעתן, bein miedatan bein shelo miedatan, whether
with their knowledge or not. I should say by the way that
the גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim says, I mean it's pretty implicit
here but the גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim just makes it explicit.
The issue came up yesterday about זכין. zachin. Can I normally like
have you as a member, you know do something for you for
your benefit? And it says that by the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
you cannot. That the only reason you can do this for the
minors is because of this principle of שה לבית seh l'vayit or
שה לבית אבות. seh l'veit avot. But if I want to say,
hey I'll do you a nice favor and I'll slaughter this for
you, it doesn't work. The idea of membership in a קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach has to be something that is done with your awareness
and knowledge. Now it could also be that there's no objective זכין
zachin because as soon as you make me a member of your
group, that disqualifies me from being a member of another group. But
anyway you could imagine scenarios where it is an objective זכין, zachin,
but the גמרא Gemara seems to say that regardless of principles of
זכין zachin which is about property ownership, the idea of being a
member is a conscious member, you know, somebody who's made an active
decision to participate in a particular group, so that with the one
exception here being about minors and slaves. Yeah. There's also a question,
remember we had a discussion in גמרא עירובין Gemara Eruvin or סומך
על שולחן אביו? somech al shulchan aviv? Oh that's very interesting. So
תוספות Tosafot asks, sometimes we do consider adults that are financially dependent
on their father to be considered like, you know, under the control
of their father. תוספות Tosafot says that would not be true here.
Actually so if you look at this על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים,
al yedei b'no u'vito haktanim, the תוספות, Tosafot, third תוספות, Tosafot, he
says פרק המביא בבבא מציעא גבי מציאה איכא מאן דאמר דלא קטן
קטן ממש אלא גדול וסמוך על שולחן אביו זהו קטן, perek hamavi
b'Bava Metzia gabi metzia ika man d'amar d'lo katan katan mamash ela
gadol v'samuch al shulchan aviv zehu katan, right, that even if an
adult who is dependent on the father is considered a minor for
certain purposes, their financial issues over there. הכא על כרחך קטן ממש,
hacha al korchacha katan mamash, דאמרינן בין מדעתו ובין שלא מדעתו, de'amrinan
bein miedato uvein shelo miedato, because we say whether with their knowledge
or not, and שלא מדעתו, shelo miedato, I told you this, not
with their knowledge is going to mean in a minute, היינו דאמרינן
לא, hainu de'amrinan lo, even if they explicitly object, not just that
they haven't voiced an opinion. He says וגדולים פשיטא דיש בידם למחות
v'gedolim peshita d'yesh beyadam limchot אפילו סמוכין על שולחן אביהן. afilu semuchin
al shulchan avihen. There's no question that adults, you know once you're
past בר מצווה, Bar Mitzvah, you're your own, you know you're independent
and you are not forced to be with your father's קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. So the idea here that they don't have any voice,
they can't even verbally object, has to be talking about minors. Okay,
so let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara
so at the end of this ברייתא, braita, וכולן ששחטו רבן עליהן
ויוצאין בשל רבן, v'chulan sheshachtu raban aleihen v'yotzin b'shel raban, I'm sorry,
yeah yeah, וכולן, v'chulan, all of these people like the slaves and
the minors, ששחטו, sheshachtu, they slaughtered their own קרבן, korban, ושחט רבן
עליהן, v'shachat raban aleihen, and their master or their father slaughtered for
them, יוצאין בשל רבן ואין יוצאין משל עצמן. yotzin b'shel raban v'ein
yotzin mishel atzman. Even if they do their own, it doesn't count.
In the end, it's the master of these non-Jewish slaves or the
father that determines whose פסח Pesach you're eating, and if he slaughtered
for you, then you're eating with his. חוץ, Chutz, the exception is
מן האישה, min ha'isha, the woman, the wife, שיכולה למחות, sheyekhola limchot,
she can protest. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא אישה, mai
shna isha, why אישה? isha? We mentioned a couple of people that
were independent, we also mentioned adult children and Jewish slaves. So אמר
רבא, amar Rava, אישה וכל דדמי לה. isha v'chol didmi la. Yeah,
we mean אישה isha and the whole group there. We mean all
the people that are, you know, that are independent. Okay, although again,
you know, given sometimes how the גמרא Gemara sees the woman as
an extension of the husband, it makes sense to particularly highlight that
the woman, you know, does have independence here. So the גמרא Gemara
says הגופא קשיא. ha gufa kashya. One minute, there's an internal contradiction.
אמרת חוץ מן האישה שיכולה למחות. amarta chutz min ha'isha sheyekhola limchot.
So you said presumably... that with the exception of the woman, the
woman can protest and say she doesn't want to be part of
it. Okay. טעמא דמחא. Ta'ma di-macha. So presumably that would be when
can a woman do it on her own, a wife, when she
protests. הא לא מחי, Ha lo machi, but it sounds like that
if she's not protesting, right? It's only when then it's לא כבשביל
בעלה, lo kishbeal ba'lah, then she would be assumed to go with
her husband. והקתני רישא בלא ידי אשתו אלא מדעתן, Ve-hakatani reisha belo
yedei ishto ella midatan, then you can't nor the wife except from
their, meaning the wife, מדעתן midatan knowledge. הסתמא לא נפקא. Ha-stama lo
nafka. So that means without any, you know, the assumption that even
the סתם stam case without her actively protesting she isn't יוצא. yotzei.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי אלא מדעתן? Mai ella midatan?
What does it mean when it says that you need their knowledge,
their buy-in? It doesn't mean that in a case of סתם stam
they... it means לאו דאמרי אין. lav de-amri in. You don't need
אלא בסתמא. ella bistama. When it says you need their knowledge, it
doesn't mean that they have to actively say yes. It is true,
in a סתם. stam* case, you'll assume that the wife wants to
be part, or the adult children want to be part. You can
go... Right, it's like the beginning, it's like our first משנה *Mishnah.
The משנה Mishnah assumes other than the question of maybe she prefers
to be with her father and, you know, her parents for יום
טוב, Yom Tov, you assume the wife would. So when it says
you need it to be מדעתן, midatan, it doesn't literally mean מדעתן.
midatan. It just means without protesting. But if she doesn't say anything,
you need דעת, da'at, but you can assume that the דעת da'at
is present. So it's required, but you could assume it's present. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא בסתמא לאפוקי היכא דאמרה לא, ella bistama
la'afukei heicha de-amerah lo, to exclude the case when she actively protests,
then she's not included. The גמרא Gemara says one minute, והא כולם
ששחטו ושחט רבן עליהן יוצאין בשל רבן. Ve-ha kulam she-shachatu ve-shachat rabban
aleihen yotzin be-shel rabban. It says that when they, they, the minor
kids or the slaves, ששחטו shachtu and the רב rav slaughters, they
are יוצא yotzei through their through what the master did. דבסתמא, De-vistama,
there they didn't actively protest and it says that there they that
you go by the master, והקתני חוץ מן האשה ve-hakatani chutz min
ha-ishah except from the wife. So if the wife שחט shachat and
her husband שחט, shachat, it says you would not go by the
husband, you'd go by the wife. That was not a case of
active protesting, so why do you go by the wife? The גמרא
Gemara says what are you talking about? והקתני חוץ מן האשה שיכולה
למחול, Ve-hakatani chutz min ha-ishah she-yecholah limchol, because she can protest. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא כיון ששחטו אין לך מחוי גדול
מזה. Amar Rava kivan she-shachtu ein lecha michuy gadol mizeh. What are
you talking about? If somebody שחט shachting their own קרבן, korban, what
more protesting do you need that they don't want to do it?
It doesn't matter, it's an active statement that I'm doing my own.
It doesn't have to mean that I'm considering the other options. I've
made a statement that I want to do my own. So basically
what you have here is the ברייתא Baraisa starts by saying that
with the minor children you don't need their דעת, da'at, which could
mean you don't need any active buy-in, but it doesn't directly address
the issue of when they actively protest, not explicitly. But in the
end it says that the wife can protest, which makes it sound
like in the wife's case, if she doesn't say anything, she's assumed
to buy in. So which do you go by? Do you assume
a סתם stam is a buy-in or not by these category of
the independent people? So the גמרא Gemara takes its leave from the
end and says yes, you're right. By the people like the wife
and the Jewish slaves and the adult children, we assume that they
without saying anything they do buy in. That's like the beginning of
our משנה. Mishnah. The wife is assumed to be part of the
husband unless she indicates otherwise. Then the חידוש chiddush becomes once that's
true, the difference between those categories and children and slaves is children
and slaves can't even if they actively protest it doesn't do them
any good, they are defined by what the master by what the
father says. And but when somebody שחט shachat on their own, that's
seen as an act of actively protesting, of actively saying I want
to do my own. And for children and slaves it won't do
any good, but for the wife it will do good and for
the wife and the adult kids it will do good. So again,
all those other people are assumed מן הסתם min ha-stam to want,
they you need their active buy-in but it's assumed to be present,
but because you need their active buy-in if they make it clear
they want to do their own thing, then they become then they
do not are not part of what the father, husband does. Yes,
Joe. Should I be bothered by the verb ששחטו she-shachtu should say
ששחטה? she-shachtah? ששחטה? she-shachtah? Well no, because it was talking about the
wife was at the end of the list, right? וכולן ששחטו. ve-chulan
she-shachtu. So ששחטו she-shachtu is a quote from the ברייתא? Baraisa? Right.
Meaning it applies the meaning of her action. Right. Exactly. But right
the grammar was wrong because it was at the end of the
list and it only counted the case of the אשה. ishah. Okay.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so there
we have this very important idea that as I said, it sort
of parallel to the physical aspect of how this חבורה chaburah is
also the question of the members. Is it the members of the
household or a group? And actually says both, and the members of
the household like children, people that are totally under the control like
children or slaves, those don't have any voice and even if they
protest it doesn't do them any good. Others are actually need a
buy-in, but you can assume that the buy-in is present. Present, and
again what's an interest- unless they opt out, what's an interesting question
that's not spelled out in the גמרא Gemara is, does the wife's
buy-in or the adult children, is that still a quasi-idea of בית?
bayis? Does it have a lower threshold than a stranger? Here, you
know, Michael and I, we do everything together. And there's no question
in our minds that we're going to eat the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach together, right? And he knows that I'm always the one that
bothers going to the market and doing things. And but we never
discussed it and I go to the market and I buy it.
Is he part of my קרבן פסח Korban Pesach or does he
have need some explicit buy-in? Maybe the wife and the children, even
though they're independent, are still, you know, can be part of the
buy-in when they don't protest and when they don't assert their independence.
So it's not a- it's an interesting question of what do you
need to be part of the חבורה, Chaburah, and can we extrapolate
from the case of the wife and the children who aren't saying
anything, or maybe there you need less because at the end of
the day, while they have independence, they're also part of the בית.
bayis. And I don't think that's clear in the גמרא. Gemara. Like,
you know, as, it's- they always, a wife and a husband do
it together. And then, you know, so her husband was like, is
he taking too long, you know, then she went and did it,
she just didn't want him to miss out. So, you know, so
she may- she may have done it just because he wasn't doing
it because he doesn't get his act together. Okay, I understand. So
that's a question of interpreting מחאה, Meichah, but I'm more interested in,
like I said, the question about what constitutes the group and what
you need to create membership in the group for קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, and whether you have three categories or two. You have people
that have no say, you have people that are assumed to buy
in but are they conceptually a distinct category? They're still a בית-type
bayis of category or not, you know, and what- that's my question,
and whether you fundamentally other people would be fundamentally a different set
of criteria. Okay, let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. So,
עבד של שני שותפין. Eved shel shnei shutfin. Now you have this
slave of two owners and he can't eat with either owner. Why
not? Even if both owners שחט shechted for him. So, רמי ליה
רב עינא סבא לרב נחמן. Rami lei Rav Einav saba l'Rav Nachman.
תנן, Tnan, עבד של שני שותפין Eved shel shnei shutfin לא יאכל
משל שניהם. lo yochal mishel shneihem. Can't eat from either of theirs.
הא דתניא, Ha d'tanya, we teach in a ברייתא, Baraita, רצה מזה
אוכל רצה מזה אוכל, ratzah mizeh ochel ratzah mizeh ochel, he could
eat from either, right? Which certainly fits into what we talked before
that you don't even need buy-in. It's sort of like the קטן
katan and the אפיטרופוס, apitropus, where once you're part of a בית,
bayis, maybe you don't even need the principle of ברירה, breirah, automatically
you're included. And if you're included in two, maybe you get to
choose. עבד כנעני Eved K'na'ani we're talking about. So what's the story?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, עינא סבא, Ina saba, which is like eye
of the elder, ואמרי ליה, v'amri lei, פתיא אוכמא, Patya Uchma, black
bread. So different types of names, I don't know if you have-
there's, you know, whether these are like- it seems like this isn't
an insult, although black bread is hard to understand how it's not
an insult, but anyway, but it's going to sound, one minute. They're
calling somebody whole wheat? Yeah. So anyway, so yeah, so various- so
these somehow are references to the fact that you're always learning תורה
Torah and you never get outdoors. It could be a reference- it
doesn't sound from the ongoing context it sounds like it's a compliment
and not an insult, insult. Okay. So, it says like this. So,
מני ומנך תסתיים שמעתתא, mini u-minach tistayem shmait'ta, between me and you
we'll figure this out. Okay. And here's the meaning of it. You
ask the question, I'll give the answer, I guess. מתניתין בדקפדי אהדדי.
Matnitin bid'kapdi ahadadei. Our משנה Mishnah is when the partners are fighting
one another and they don't want to, you know, nobody wants anyone,
you know, to do anything to benefit the other person, or to
derive benefit from the other person. So I don't want- so if
my- if I'm going to have the slave eat with me, you
who's my partner who's angry at me says, uh-uh, I refuse for
my slave to get benefit from you. I don't- you know, I
forswear any benefit from you, which means my slave can't get any
benefit from you. So therefore he's not allowed to participate in mine
because you won't allow it, and he's not allowed to participate in
yours because I won't allow it. Okay. Thinking of a קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, you pay for it. Okay, right, exactly. ברייתא דלא קפדי
אהדדי. Baraita d'lo kapdi ahadadei. The ברייתא Baraita is if they don't
care, they're all friendly. And if they're all friendly, then therefore he
can eat with either one. So, by the way, even in the
case of eating with either one, it's like the- it's like the
minor with the אפיטרופסין, apitropsin, right, with the two guardians who are,
you know, and therefore can objectively be defined as part of two
households, and there somehow the issue of ברירה breirah is no longer
an issue because objectively he's part of a household, it's not an
issue of his choice, so he has- then he can choose which
one because either one will be legitimate because he's part of either
household. The חידוש chiddush is that when they're angry at one another,
the fact that you can refuse, it's my property and he can't
be with you, you know, that prevents him from being considered part
of your household and vice versa, part of mine. Okay. מי שחציו
עבד וחציו בן חורין לא יאכל משל רבו. Mi shechetzyo eved v'chetzyo
ben chorin lo yochal mishel rabbo. Now, if somebody's half slave and
half free, he can't eat with his master without get- you know,
without his master saying it's okay, because the assumption could be that
the master might not want, you know, sure, half of you is
part of my household, but I didn't say that I want the
other half to be part of my household. It's a part of
my חבורת פסח, chavurat pesach, and therefore you cannot eat, you cannot
eat unless you have the explicit buy-in from the master. Yeah. So
the גמרא Gemara says you'd eat a כזית kezayit exactly. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says משל רבו הוא דלא יאכל אבל משלו יאכל.
Mishel rabo hu delo yochal aval mishelo yochal. Wait a minute. This
sounds like okay, but what I can do is go שחט shacht
my own קרבן פסח korban pesach and eat it. והתניא Ve-hatanya לא
יאכל לא משל רבו ולא משלו. lo yochal lo mishel rabo velo
mishelo. I can't even eat my own קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Why?
Same logic as before. You, my master, will say I never gave
that slave part of you right to eat with somebody else's קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, right? So you're sort of stuck between the two.
He doesn't give the free part of me, he didn't allow that
to be part of the group, but he doesn't give the slave
part of me the right to eat on my own. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so לא קשיא. lo kashya. It's not difficult. כאן
כמשנה ראשונה וכאן כמשנה אחרונה. Kan kemishna rishona vekan kemishna achrona. It
depends whether it's like the first משנה mishna or the second משנה.
mishna. What does that mean? דתנן, Detnan, by the way this phrase
משנה אחרונה mishna achrona משנה ראשונה mishna rishona shows, doesn't just that
there really is this history of the editing of the משנה. mishna.
There are early layers and so on which the גמרא Gemara makes
explicit reference to in multiple times. Anyway, actually sometimes in the משנה
mishna itself. דתנן, Detnan, מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין, mi she-chetzyo
eved ve-chetzyo ben chorin, somebody's half slave half free. He had two
partners, one of them freed him. What's the story? So עובד את
רבו יום אחד ואת עצמו יום אחד. Oved et rabo yom echad
ve-et atzmo yom echad. Fine. So his, you know, his profits, his
labors half to his master and half to himself. He's one day
on one day off. דברי בית הלל. Divrei Beit Hillel. That's what
בית הלל Beit Hillel says. אמרו בית שמאי לבית הלל, Amru Beit
Shammai le-Beit Hillel, תקנתם את רבו ואת עצמו לא תקנתם. Tikantem et
rabo ve-et atzmo lo tikantem. It's very nice you helped the master,
but you didn't help the slave himself. Now, it's interesting, normally we
think of בית הלל Beit Hillel as the one being more sort
of sympathetic to human issues. Here בית שמאי Beit Shammai is the
one that's coming to defend the slave. Now, they do it with
הלכה halacha language and here's what they say. לישא שפחה אינו יכול,
Lisha shifcha eino yachol, to marry a maidservant he's not able to
because שכבר חציו בן חורין, she-kevar chetzyo ben chorin, he's half a
free person. לישא בת חורין אינו יכול, Lisha bat chorin eino yachol,
he can't marry a free woman שכבר חציו עבד she-kevar chetzyo eved
and that's the prohibition of a slave and a free woman or
a slave woman and a free man. So יבטל? Yibatel? Should you
tell me he shouldn't have kids? והלא לא נברא העולם אלא לפרייה
ורבייה. Ve-halo lo nivra ha-olam ela le-pirya ve-rivya. The world was created
for פריה ורביה. pirya ve-rivya. שנאמר לא תהו בראה לשבת יצרה. Shenemar
lo tohu vera’ah lashevet yetzarah. God didn't create it to be desolate
but to be settled. So obviously we can't let this guy not
have kids. So what are you going to do? אלא מפני תיקון
העולם, Ela mipnei tikkun ha-olam, for the sake of establishing the world,
כופין את רבו ועושה אותו בן חורין. Kofin et rabo ve-oseh oto
ben chorin. You force the master that still has him as a
slave to free him. וכותב שטר על חצי דמיו Ve-kotev shtar al
chatzi damav and he owes that value, half of his value, he
owes it as a debt. But he's a free man. So therefore,
according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, even while it has not yet
happened, we're going to make sure that it does happen. And since
we as חז״ל Chazal are going to make sure that it does
happen, even now he can operate largely as a free man, meaning
it's true his status is half slave half free, but the master
no longer has control over him to dictate what he can and
can't do because we're going to, we are going to force the
master to free him. So personal status is half and half but
the master's control has ended. And therefore he's allowed to go ahead,
go off and do his own קרבן פסח. korban pesach. וחזרו בית
הלל להורות כבית שמאי. Ve-chazru Beit Hillel le-horot ke-Beit Shammai. And then
בית הלל Beit Hillel came around to teaching like בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. Yes, go ahead. Rivka was talking specifically and I wanted to
add much more so for an עגונה aguna that is similarly in
this limbo status. Not free, half-free, she's not free. And he uses
an עבד eved and this applies to a woman as well, to
a female, that has חרות herut to populate God's world, because that's
what God wants. How much more so for a Jewish woman. We
are obligated to free her so that she can remarry and have
children. Amen. Amen. Thank you. So just to make sure I'm following.
So there's the תניא tanya or I guess the תנן tenan that's
really משנה ראשונה mishna rishona anyway is when it says לא יאכל
לא משלו ולא משל רבו lo yochal lo mishelo velo mishel rabo
is the משנה ראשונה, mishna rishona, right? Which was subsequently edited out
by our משנה mishna because our משנה... mishna... No, no, no. משנה
ראשונה mishna rishona משנה אחרונה mishna achrona here refers to the two
layers or the two stages in this משנה mishna that was quoted
about בית הלל בית שמאי. Beit Hillel Beit Shammai. And it's saying
this ברייתא braita goes like the end of that discussion, the end
of that משנה. mishna. And our משנה mishna goes like the later
משנה. mishna. And our משנה mishna is לא יאכל משל רבו, lo
yochal mishel rabo, right? Which he can't. Oh, I'm sorry, right. Our
משנה mishna goes like the conclusion and the ברייתא braita goes like
the first משנה. mishna. Correct. I do want to also point out
about the issue of פריה ורביה. pirya ve-rivya. It's an interesting question
why the גמרא Gemara quoted the principle of לא תהו בראה lo
tohu vera’ah and there's a fascinating debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
an עבד eved is חייב, chayav, a full עבד eved is חייב
chayav in פריה ורביה, pirya ve-rivya, the מצווה. mitzvah. Because if we
פוסקין pasken like we tend to do that, I mean it's a
debate in the גמרא Gemara and the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi not conclusive, but
it seems like the גמרא's Gemara conclusion is that... only men are
חייב hayyav in פרו ורבו, pru u'revu, so then the question is
how about an עבד? eved? So normally we say an עבד eved
has the same מצוות mitzvot as a woman, but what about this?
So it gets to an interesting question of whether the man's obligation
in פרו ורבו pru u'revu has something to do with maleness, you
know, or does it or is it just sort of this like,
you know, sort of this arbitrary type of law? So would a
slave who is, you know, biologically male but has normally the מצוות
mitzvot of a woman, would he have the מצוה mitzvah of פרו
ורבו pru u'revu or not? So there's actually an interesting debate in
the ראשונים. Rishonim. Some say, well, if they had to quote a
פסוק pasuk of לא תהו בראה, lo tohu bera'ah, why didn't they
just say דכתיב dichtiv פרו ורבו? pru u'revu? So it shows that
he only has, it's more this value of settling the world, but
not the actual מצוה. mitzvah. Others say no, you know, okay, if
it was just the מצוה, mitzvah, fine, he's an אונס, ones, he
has a מצוה mitzvah he can't do it, but if we want
to make a point that this is not a מצוה mitzvah we're
willing to be מוותר mevater on, you know, this is a מצוה
mitzvah we want to make sure gets done because it's such a
weighty מצוה. mitzvah. But again, so the question is why did they
make reference to this big value לא תהו lo tohu and not
talk in more limited technical terms of the מצוה? mitzvah? So some
say it proves he doesn't have the מצוה mitzvah like women, according
to the פרט perat that women aren't obligated in פרו ורבו, pru
u'revu, and others say no, he does, but that wouldn't have been
enough to motivate us were it not for this value. And that
then leads to the comparable discussion which is תוספות Tosafot assert, תוספות'ס
Tosafot's approach that slaves don't have the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו
pru u'revu and nevertheless we can invoke this value of לא תהו
בראה, lo tohu bera'ah, and that for תוספות, Tosafot, this idea of
לא תהו בראה lo tohu bera'ah becomes a mandate for women as
well, because his whole point is to see slaves and women in
the same way, and that becomes another fascinating discussion which is, is
there some element of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו pru u'revu
that applies to women as well and not just to men? So
a lot of interesting thing comes from the, from which type of
arguments are made here with בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. That's a sub-discussion
that I do not want to get into it. That's gonna lead
to a nice discussion and debate and I'm not ready to have
that right now. Yeah, I agree with you, you do not leave
a person in this limbo situation. Right, exactly. Exactly. Exactly. And it's
interesting because on both sides there's this meta-halachic, you know, value system.
Right, both agree whatever the reason is we're still quoting a value
and not just the narrow הלכה halacha as part of what motivates
this תקנה, takkana, absolutely. Absolutely. Absolutely. Okay, so let's look at the
next משנה. Mishnah. האומר לעבדו, Ha-omer l'avdo, somebody who says to a
servant, and we've been talking about servants as property, here it's, it's
a little bit related to specifically being a servant, but part of
this could be part of this issue could be discussed regardless of
being a servant, just being an agent and a messenger for me.
So anyway, I say, somebody says to a servant, צא ושחוט עלי
את הפסח, tzei u'shchot alai et ha-Pesach, go shecht the פסח Pesach
for me. By the way, interesting, here you have a slave שחטינג
shechting the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, right? So I mean, okay, you
know, as we said, doesn't have to be כהנים, Kohanim, men, women,
slaves can do the שחיטה shechitah of קרבנות. korbanot. Can they be
an עבד? eved? Can it be an עבד כנעני eved Kena'ani doing
a שחיטה? shechitah? Yeah, yeah, yes they can, that's why I'm pointing
it out. Now, שחט גדי יאכל. shachat gedi yochal. So let, you
didn't say, I didn't say which one I preferred, even though I'm
known to have a preference for lamb steaks, you went ahead and
you did a goat. Okay, since I didn't specify, fine, that counts
and I eat it. שחט טלה, shachat taleh, you did a lamb
and I known to prefer goat meat, nevertheless, יאכל, yochal, I should,
I eat it. Now, שחט גדי וטלה, shachat gedi v'taleh, the slave
didn't know so he said better play it safe and שחט shachat
both. So therefore you can't be part of two פסח'ס. Pesachs. So
יאכל מן הראשון, yochal min ha-rishon, you eat from the first one
that he, that he שחט shachat presumably, that's the one that we'll
go by. That I assume since not specified presumably go by the
first one. So the question should be, was he actually not allowed
to like be on two, three? Yeah, right, fine, it was a
mistake. Okay. שכח מה אמר לו רבו. shachach mah amar lo rabbo.
Now, master actually said something but he forgot what. So כיצד יעשה?
keitzad ya'aseh? What should he do? So he can't say I'll just
שחט shachat both, it'll be either well he could, but how, but
now at least that he's thinking ahead of time how's he going
to do best to play, cover his bases. ישחוט טלה וגדי, yishchot
taleh v'gedi, שחט shachat both, but here's how you are even better
and covering your bases, ויאמר, v'yomar, אם גדי אמר לי רבי, im
gedi amar li rabbi, if my master, רבו rabbo it should probably
be, if my master told me a goat, גדי שלו וטלה שלי,
gedi shelo v'taleh sheli, his will be the גדי gedi and I'll
have and I'll use the טלה taleh for my קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. ואם טלה אמר לי רבי, v'im taleh amar li rabbi, and
if he said טלה, taleh, הטלה שלו וגדי שלי. ha-taleh shelo v'gedi
sheli. So now they're both good קרבנות, korbanot, you just don't know
whose is whose, right? If he שחט'ד shachat'd both and he didn't
make this stipulation then one of them wouldn't be a good קרבן.
korban. This way they're both good קרבנות. korbanot. The only problem is
who eats what, because you can't eat a פסח Pesach that's not
your, that you're not part of that's not your פסח. Pesach. So
what's the הלכה? halacha? So the הלכה halacha is, הטלה שלו וגדי
שלי. ha-taleh shelo v'gedi sheli. But presumably in that case, I'm jumping
ahead to the end of the משנה, Mishnah, you go back and
you ask your רבי, rabbi, the master what he said, and then
you figure out whose is whose. Now, שכח רבו מה אמר לו,
shachach rabbo mah amar lo, then you go back to the master,
it says, okay, I forgot which one did you say? He says,
oh no, I forgot that, weren't you paying attention? So מה אמר
לו? mah amar lo? So now nobody knows, but each one was
יוצא, yotzei, we just don't know whose is whose. In that case,
שניהם יצאו. sheneihem yatze'u. ופטורין מלעשות פסח שני, u'pturin mila'asot pesach sheni,
but everybody's exempt because again, this is what I've been telling you.
If when the קרבן korban was brought it was fit to be
eaten, then even if the meat isn't eaten, you're יוצא yotzei your
obligation of the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. You weren't יוצא yotzei obligation
of eating the meat that night, you know same way maybe I
didn't eat מצה matzah that night, but I was still יוצא yotzei
the קרבן korban because when it was brought it was fit to
be eaten. Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara.
פשיטא שחט גדי יאכל, pshita shachat gedi yochal, obviously אף על גב
דרגיל בטלה. af al gav deragil betleh. שחט טלה יאכל. shachat tleh
yochal. I'm sorry, פשיטא, pshita, isn't this all obvious? That it's you
know, if he didn't tell you you do it, you know, you
go ahead and if he didn't specify then it's whatever I do.
So the משנה mishna says שחט גדי יאכל אף על גב דרגיל
בטלה, shachat gedi yochal af al gav deragil betleh, שחט טלה יאכל
אף על גב דרגיל בגדי. shachat tleh yochal af al gav deragil
begdi. Okay, so it doesn't matter. The point that's added that's not
explicit in the משנה mishna is it doesn't matter if I normally
have a preference, if I didn't say, then it's whatever you choose.
Now, שחט גדי וטלה יאכל מן הראשון. shachat gedi vetleh yochal min
harishon. Now, is it really true going to the next line of
the משנה? mishna? So the חידוש chidush of the first part is
even if I normally have a preference, if I didn't say it,
tough luck. שחט גדי וטלה יאכל מן הראשון, shachat gedi vetleh yochal
min harishon, is that really true? והתניא אין נמנין על שני פסחים
כאחד, vehatanya ein nimnin al shenei pesachim k'echad, that you can't be
part of two פסחים Pesachs at the same time. Now, why is
that? Meaning, meaning I can't choose after it's shechted which one I
prefer. So why here do you get to go by the first
one? So רש"י Rashi says now, of course the funny thing is
that if I didn't specify, why isn't the first one just objectively
defined as that's the one I shechted as the פסח? Pesach? I
didn't specify, that becomes automatically the one. So תוספות Tosfos spells out
it's not exactly clear why that's a problem. So if you take
a look at the last line of תוספות, Tosfos, והתניא, vehatanya, two
lines above where it says במלך, bemelech, תוספות Tosfos says יש לומר
דמתניתין קאמר ראשון לשחיטה yesh lomar dematnitin kamar rishon lishchita שהימנו עליו
לבסוף. shehinnu alav lebasof. So that... one minute... oh, he distinguishes between
the שחיטה shchita and the מעשה מינוי. maise minui. Yeah, but one
minute, let me just check the תוספות Tosfos again. One minute. Yeah,
I think what תוספות Tosfos says is that the משנה, mishna, meaning
you know why don't you just say, meaning it's hard to understand
exactly the גמרא's Gemara question, because since we said when I don't
specify it's whatever the slave chooses, so why don't we say here:
I didn't specify, he chose, he chose A and then he chose
B, the first one he chose was A, so it's A, obviously
it should be A. So what's the big question, I can't be
part of two פסח? Pesach? So תוספות Tosfos says, he says that
the sense is it's which one the slave shechted first is mine,
even though if the slave took a sheep and a goat and
he said okay the sheep will be his, and then he said
okay the goat will be his and then he shechted the goat
first. So that's what's bothering it, that it seems to go by
which one the slave shechted first even though the slave sort of
assigned it to me the master second, it still goes by the
one he shechted first. So the גמרא Gemara says why should that
be the case? Okay, again it's not exactly clear why this is
so bothered, but let's see where it goes with this. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניתין במלך ומלכא. matnitin bemelech umalka. The
משנה mishna is talking about a king and a queen, or people
in a similar category. What does this mean? והתניא vehatanya as we
taught in the ברייתא, braisa, this isn't a question it's a proof.
אין נמנין על שני פסחים כאחד. ein nimnin al shenei pesachim k'echad.
You cannot say I'm going to be part of two groups and
then I'll decide later. Okay. מעשה במלך ומלכא שאמרו לעבדיהם, maise bemelech
umalka she'amru le'avdehem, there's a story about a king and a queen
that said to their servants, צא ושחוט עלינו את הפסח, tzei vishchot
aleinu et hapesach, go shecht us a פסח. Pesach. ויצא ושחט עליהם
שני פסחים, veyatza vishachat aleihem shenei pesachim, and they went and they
did two, one a goat and one a lamb. באו ושאלו את
המלך, ba'u vishalu et hamelech, they asked the king, what should we
do? Right? Which one? Some of us did a goat, some did
a lamb, which is which? אמר להם לכו ושאלו את המלכה, amar
lahem lechu vishalu et hamalka, go ask the queen, she knows. Now,
as we're going to see later in the story, it's not just
she knows what we prefer to eat for dinner, but she knows
הלכה halacha better. So presumably this is talking about one of the...
חשמונאים Chashmonaim kings? Yeah, it's not explicitly שלומציון, Shlomtzion, but anyway, somewhere
in the... of the חשמונאים Chashmonaim kings. So go ask the queen.
So באו ושאלו מן המלכה, ba'u vishalu min hamalka, they asked the
queen. אמרה להם לכו ושאלו את רבן גמליאל, amra lahem lechu vishalu
et Rabban Gamliel, go ask רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So I didn't
do the dating, but her brother? שלומציון Shlomtzion was רבן גמליאל's Rabban
Gamliel brother? Or I mean שלומציון... Shlomtzion... ינאי Yannai I believe was...
the husband, the husband. Okay, so that makes sense then. That makes
sense. Okay. Everybody שמעון בן שטח. Shimon ben Shetach. Not רבן גמליאל.
Rabban Gamliel. I'll have to figure out the dating here. Ba'u v'sha'alu
et Rabban Gamliel (באו ושאלו את רבן גמליאל *Ba'u v'sha'alu et Rabban
Gamliel*), they asked Rabban Gamliel (רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*). Amar la'hem (אמר
להם *Amar la'hem*): mashlu l'melekh (משלו למלך *mashlu l'melekh*) that if a
king קלה עליהם *kalla aleihem*. It's not necessarily something you want to
be saying about a king and queen, but here it means that,
you know, they don't care. You know, they have so many delicacies.
They're not makpid (מקפיד *makpid*) tonight are we having lamb chops or
are we having goat meat? You know, they can have any types
of delicacies they want, so it really doesn't matter much one or
the other. So in that case, yokhlu min harishon (יאכלו מן הראשון
*yokhlu min harishon*). They'll eat from the first one. They'll want whichever
one is shechted first. Anan, lo nokhal lo min harishon v'lo min
hasheni (אנן לא נאכל לא מן הראשון ולא מן השני *Anan lo
nokhal lo min harishon v'lo min hasheni*). We, if something like this
would happen to us, so we would be stuck because we wouldn't
be able to eat from the first or the second because it
would be a question of which one we preferred. And since we
had not made explicit which one we preferred, it would be not
able to determine which one was actually ours. Okay, b'shuv pa'am achat
(בשוב פעם אחת *b'shuv pa'am achat*). Now, we have another similar story.
Nimtzat haltza'ah b'veit hamisbechayim (נמצאת הלטאה בבית המטבחיים *Nimtzat haltza'ah b'veit hamisbechayim*).
All right, they found like a lizard, a dead lizard in the,
in the, in like the kitchen, and they thought that it was
one of the things that caused tumah (טומאה *tumah*), and we're going
to find out that the king and the queen ate everything b'taharah
(בטהרה *b'taharah*). V'bikshu l'tamei kol hase'udah kullah (ובקשו לטמא כל הסעודה כולה
*V'bikshu l'tamei kol hase'udah kullah*). They said, oh my God, the whole
meal is tamei (טמא *tamei*) and nobody can eat from it if
we're all eating our chullin b'taharah (חולין בטהרה *chullin b'taharah*). Ba'u v'sha'alu
et hamelekh (באו ושאלו את המלך *Ba'u v'sha'alu et hamelekh*), they asked
the king what should we do. Amar la'hem (אמר להם *Amar la'hem*):
l'khu v'sha'alu et hamalkah (לכו ושאלו את המלכה *l'khu v'sha'alu et hamalkah*),
go ask the queen. Ba'u v'sha'alu et hamalkah (באו ושאלו את המלכה
*Ba'u v'sha'alu et hamalkah*), they asked the queen. Amar la'hem (אמר להם
*Amar la'hem*): l'khu v'sha'alu et Rabban Gamliel (לכו ושאלו את רבן גמליאל
*l'khu v'sha'alu et Rabban Gamliel*), go ask Rabban Gamliel (רבן גמליאל *Rabban
Gamliel*). So that would make Rabban Gamliel (רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*) the
snake then. No, he's not the snake... the reverse of Gan Eden
(גן עדן *Gan Eden*). Ba'u v'sha'alu'o (באו ושאלוהו *Ba'u v'sha'alu'o*), they asked
him. Amar la'hem (אמר להם *Amar la'hem*): beit hamisbechayim shelakhem rotayach o
tzonen (בית המטבחיים שלכם רותח או צונן *beit hamisbechayim shelakhem rotayach o
tzonen*)? Is your kitchen hot or cool? Amru lo (אמרו לו *Amru
lo*): rotayach (רותח *rotayach*). They said to him, it's hot. Amar la'hem
(אמר להם *Amar la'hem*): lekhu v'hatilu aleiha kos shel tzonen (לכו והטילו
עליה כוס של צונן *lekhu v'hatilu aleiha kos shel tzonen*), go take
that lizard and throw on it a cup of cold water. Halkhu
v'hitilu aleiha kos shel tzonen (הלכו והטילו עליה כוס של צונן *Halkhu
v'hitilu aleiha kos shel tzonen*), they threw on it a cup of
cold water, v'rikhshah (ורכשה *v'rikhshah*), it started thrashing around, so it wasn't
dead, it was just, you know, it was just exhausted, fainted from
the heat. So it wasn't dead. V'tihar Rabban Gamliel kol hase'udah kullah
(וטהר רבן גמליאל כל הסעודה כולה *V'tihar Rabban Gamliel kol hase'udah kullah*).
So he said the entire meal was okay. Nimtza melekh talui b'malkah
(נמצא מלך תלוי במלכה *Nimtza melekh talui b'malkah*), you see that the
king is dependent on the queen. V'nimtza malkah teluyah b'Rabban Gamliel (ונמצא
מלכה תלויה ברבן גמליאל *V'nimtza malkah teluyah b'Rabban Gamliel*), and the queen
is dependent on Rabban Gamliel (רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*). Nimtza kol hase'udah
teluyah b'Rabban Gamliel (נמצא כל הסעודה תלויה ברבן גמליאל *Nimtza kol hase'udah
teluyah b'Rabban Gamliel*), the whole meal... I'd rather have the king and
queen dependent on me than the whole meal, to be honest. But
okay. It's a metaphor. The whole world is dependent on the talmidei
chakhamim (תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chakhamim*). Right, exactly. But didn't the mishna (משנה
Mishna *mishna*) at some point say something about the implications of what
nashim da'atan kallah (נשים דעתן קלה *nashim da'atan kallah*) means now? So
yeah, like nashim da'atan kallah (נשים דעתן קלה *nashim da'atan kallah*). Yeah,
and here it's right, it's not meant as a pejorative. It means
like, yeah, they don't really care. Right. So I don't know if
you can use that in other, you know, if that works in
like the whole discussion about the nashim da'atan kallah (נשים דעתן קלה
*nashim da'atan kallah*) discussion. Because here it really means like, yeah, you
know, they have it so good they really don't care one way
or the other. They don't, they don't treat... it's not a weighty
issue for them. Right. It's, you know, these are not weighty decisions.
So I guess in other ways it can be a pejorative, which
means you don't give things proper weight. You know, here it's about
what food you prefer, it doesn't matter if you make it a
weighty decision or not. Okay, but I do have to say that
I'm not really still not clear to me what exactly is bothering
the Gemara (גמרא Gemara *Gemara*) here. Once you say that you don't
specify, why don't you just go to the one that was picked
first? And if the reality is that it was, you know, they,
they sort of... that they... that it was picked at the same
time but was picked in the reverse order. Again, why should you
go by the one that was shechted first, not the one that
was picked first? Again, it's not exactly clear to me what the
conclusion here is. Right, but someone really did it. Yeah, I mean,
in the case by the king and the queen, if they said,
"Okay, they don't really care, so go by the rishon (ראשון *rishon*),"
so does rishon (ראשון *rishon*) mean the one that was designated first?
I suppose. But if that's true, then that's what it means also
in the mishna (משנה *mishna*), designated first. So then I guess I
don't know why you need melekh v'malkah (מלך ומלכה *melekh v'malkah*). Since
if you only did one, it would be your option to pick
which one, if you did two, it should just go by the
one that you had done first, you know? So I don't really
get why you need the melekh v'malkah (מלך ומלכה *melekh v'malkah*) and
how that changes it. Anyway. All right. Now, shachach mah amar lo
rabbo (שכח מה אמר לו רבו *shachach mah amar lo rabbo*). So
if he'd forgot what the rav (רב *rav*) said, then he makes...
then he says, you know, I'll take two, and one will be
mine, and one will be his, and we'll ask my master later
which is which. And Gemara (גמרא Gemara *Gemara*) says, "sheli (שלי *sheli*),
this one is mine," how could that be? Mah shekanah eved kanah
rabbo (מה שקנה עבד קנה רבו *Mah shekanah eved kanah rabbo*). A
slave can't have independent ownership. Whatever a slave owns, his master owns.
And here it's relevant that he's a slave (עבד *eved*). So amar
Abaye (אמר אביי Amar Abaye, *amar Abaye*): holikh eitzel ro'eh haragil rabbo
etzlo (הוליך אצל רועה הרגיל רבו אצלו *holikh eitzel ro'eh haragil rabbo
etzlo*). You go by a shepherd that my master normally has dealings
with. V'nichlei b'takanta d'rabbeh (וניחא ליה בתקנתא דרביה *V'nichlei b'takanta d'rabbeh*). And
the shepherd wants to help out because he, you know, whatever, he'll
get better business in the future, so he wants to make things
work here. So what do you do? U'makni leih chad minaihu (ומקני
ליה חד מנייהו *U'makni leih chad minaihu*) and he gives him one
of them, a sheep or a goat, v'amar (ואמר *v'amar*): al mnat
she'ein l'rabbo reshut bo (על מנת שאין לרבו רשות reshus בו *al
mnat she'ein l'rabbo reshut bo*). He says, look, I'm giving you two...
the sheep and a goat, and he knows he's going to get
paid back by the master, so he knows the master will want
what works better for everyone. And he says one of them I'm
giving to, what I'm giving you is I'm selling to you, the
other I'm giving you for free, it's the one that your master
didn't say. If your master said sheep then it's the goat, if
the goat then it's the sheep, and that one I'm giving you
on the stipulation that it's yours and your master doesn't have ownership.
And you actually, interestingly, can do that. It is possible according to
the גמרא Gemara for slaves to have independent ownership provided that they,
what do you call it, provided that it's explicitly stipulated that you
do not mean for it to continue to the master. Okay, so
which is interesting, you could have said there's no idea at all
of independent ownership.
Here we see no, basically what happens under normal circumstances is I
give you something, it sort of stops momentarily
into your account and then it like automatically gets transferred into your
master's account. But if I can make it, if I'm the one
who's giving it and I stipulate that won't happen, it actually can
stop in your account as well. In Rome, I should say, slaves
had their own property and sometimes slaves were extremely wealthy, depending on
who their masters were and so on. But it is a חידוש,
chidush, we're so used to the idea that a slave isn't his
own רשות and he's an extension of his master. Here we see
that you actually can make the property stop at the slave if
you stipulate. This is just a kickback. He's bribing the food and
beverage manager for future... That's a good point actually. And once he
has this ability, that's actually probably how slaves in Rome did get
wealthy. It's a good... but here it's not a kickback. The whole
idea is the master would want it because it'll let things work
out. That's like the מחלוקת machlokes בקידושין be'Kiddushin that a slave משחרר
meshachrer himself עם כסף im kesef and then it's like על ידי
אחרים al yedei acheirim or not על ידי אחרים? al yedei acheirim?
Yes, yes, that's similar discussion there. Exactly. All right, let's read a
little more. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, now we get the last part,
the master doesn't remember, so they all get burnt but everybody was
יוצא yotze because each one had a קרבן. korban. שכח רבו מה
אמר שאמר לו. Shachach rabbo mah amar she'amar lo. אמר אביי לא
שנו אלא ששכח אחר זריקה. Amar Abaye lo shanu ela sheshachach achar
zrika. That's only if he forgot after the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam.
דבעידנא דאיזרק דם הוי חזי לאכילה, De'be'idana de'izreik dam havi chazi la'achila,
that when the blood was being thrown, the master at least knew
whose was whose and each one was theoretically fit to be eaten.
אבל שכח לפני זריקה, Aval shachach lifnei zrika, if the master forgot
before the blood, so neither the slave nor the master knows whose
is whose, so even though the קרבן korban is כשר, kasher, nobody
is able to eat it at the time of זריקת הדם. zrikas
hadam. Nobody knows whose is whose. דכי איזרק דם לא הוי חזי
לאכילה, De'chi izreik dam lo havi chazi la'achila, when the blood was
thrown it wasn't fit to be eaten. חייבין לעשות פסח שני, Chayavin
la'asos Pesach Sheni, then they have to do פסח שני Pesach Sheni
because it wasn't fit to be eaten. איכא דמתני לה אברייתא, Ikka
de'matni la'abraisa, some say this statement of אביי Abaye goes on a
ברייתא. braisa. חמישה שנתערבו עורות פסיחיהם זה בזה, Chamisha shenisarvu oros pischon
zeh bazeh, five people had the skin of their פסח Pesach mixed
up. So who cares, you're not going to eat the skin? But
then somebody started looking at the skins. ונמצא יבלת באחד מהן, Ve'nimtza
yabelles be'echad mehen, and found one of the skins had a wart
and actually had a מום. mum. So one of our פסח Pesachs
has a מום, mum, but we don't know whose because the skins
are mixed up, we don't know whose is whose. כולם יצאו לבית
השריפה ופטורים מלעשות פסח שני. Kulan yetzu leveit hasreifa u'pturim m'la'asos Pesach
Sheni. You burn them all and we're exempt from פסח שני Pesach
Sheni because they were all good. Now they weren't all good. One
of us should be חייב chayav in a פסח שני Pesach Sheni
and we'll discuss that later. But anyway, four of us are exempt.
Okay, so in that case, איכא דמתני... ikka de'matni... where are we?
אמר אביי, Abaye so there we have אביי said: לא שנו אלא
שנתערבו אחר זריקה. Lo shanu ela shenisarvu achar zrika. That's only if
it got mixed up after זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. דבעידנא דאיזדרוק דם
מיחזא הוי חזי לאכילה. De'be'idana de'izdaruk dam michza havi chazi la'achila. When
the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam took place, four of them were fit
to be eaten and it was known which was which, or could
have been known. אבל נתערבו לפני זריקה, Aval nisarvu lifnei zrika, there
must have been a big pause because you had enough time to
flay it before you did the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. But okay,
if they got mixed up before זריקה zrika and then when the
זריקת הדם zrikas hadam was done, it was not knowable whose was
edible, then חייב לעשות פסח שני, chayav la'asos Pesach Sheni, you have
to. Now the גמרא says it's not necessarily that these have the
same הלכה. halacha. מאן דמתני אמתניתין, Man de'matni amasnithin, if אביי'ס Abaye's
point that if he forgot, they have to do a פסח שני
Pesach Sheni if they forgot before זריקה, zrika, if you say it's
on the משנה that if it happened before זריקה, zrika, כל שכן
אברייתא, kol sheken abraisa, certainly in the case about when there's a
מום. mum. But מאן דמתני אברייתא, man de'matni abraisa, but if you
say it on the ברייתא, braisa, that if it got mixed up
before you have to bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, אבל אמתניתין
לא, aval amasnithin lo, by the case of forgetting, even if you
forgot beforehand, you could say that you wouldn't have to bring a
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. כיון דכשירה נינהו, Keivan de'kshere ninhu, both of
the קרבנות korbanot are כשר, kasher, both the sheep and the goat.
The only problem is you idiots don't know whose is whose. דאידכר
הוי חזי לאכילה, De'idkar havi chazi la'achila, and if you remembered, even
though you didn't know when the blood was being thrown, who knows?
Maybe later you'll figure it out and you'll remember it and you'll
be able to eat it. ולקמי שמיא גליא, U'lkamei shamayia galya, it's
known by heaven, objectively, you have two כשר kasher פסח. Pesach. Just
because you are ignorant, you don't know which one you can eat.
Funny to say שמיא גליא. shamayia galya. So that is בחפצא, be'cheftza,
as we would say in ישיביש yeshivish language, ראוי לאכילה. rui la'achila.
Just you personally can't eat it because you don't remember. As opposed
to the case of the מום, mum, in that case where one
of them can't be eaten and you don't know which one, that's
seen as that all of them can be considered not fit to
be eaten from the very object itself. One last line, אמר מר,
Amar Mar, פטורין מלעשות פסח שני, pturin mila'asot Pesach Sheni, ואיכא חד
דלא נפיש. ve'ika chad delo nafish. What do you mean, that we're
all exempt from פסח שני Pesach Sheni when there was a מום
mum on one of them? Even if four were good, one is
not good. So the גמרא says, משום דלא אפשר, mishum delo efshar,
because there's no way that we can do a פסח שני Pesach
Sheni even for the guy who is obligated, we don't know who
he is. היכי לעביד, Heichi le'avid, what do you want us to
do? ליתי כל חד וחד פסח, Leiti kol chad vechad pesach, if
you say we should all bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, קא
מייתי חולין לעזרה, ka meiti chulin la'azara, then four of those are
not valid sacrifices, דארבעה מינייהו עבדו להו, de'arba mineihu avdu lehu, דארבעה
מינייהו עבדו להו, de'arba mineihu avdu lehu, four of us have brought
a פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. ליתי כולהו חד פסח, Leiti kulu chad
pesach, let us all bring one פסח Pesach and all be like
make a, you know, be a group and be a, you know,
be a חבורה chabura for one פסח Pesach for the פסח שני
Pesach Sheni and one of us is the one obligated in it.
נמצא פסח נאכל שלא למנויו, Nimtza pesach ne'echal shelo limnu'av, the פסח
Pesach will be eaten by people that are not counted on it.
Of course, why don't we just say that nobody eats it, but
we all bring it? But again, if nobody's eating it, then it's
not fit to be eaten again. You have to have it that
the second one at least is fit to be eaten. So פסח
שני Pesach Sheni I can't invite my neighbor to eat in, you
know I can say, "Hi, join me for פסח"? Pesach No. No.
הי מאי, Hei mai, נמצא פסח נאכל שלא למנויו? nimtza pesach ne'echal
shelo limnu'av? ואי עבדי חבורה Ve'i avdi chabura for פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. Yes, but four of us aren't obligated in פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. So what? If you שחט shacht it למנויו ושלא למנויו, limnu'av
veshelo limnu'av, it's okay. Yes, but then nobody can eat it. That's
why if we should all eat it, if we're all going to
eat it, then four people are going to be over on an
עבירה aveira of eating a פסח שלא למנויו. Pesach shelo limnu'av. If
nobody eats it, then it wasn't ראוי לאכילה. rauy la'achila. So you're
back to square one. Oh wait, but meaning I thought the הלכה
halacha is that if you שחט shacht it למנויו ושלא למנויו? limnu'av
veshelo limnu'av? Yes, the שחיטה shechita was okay, but it's not going
to be ראוי לאכילה rauy la'achila if nobody can eat it. So
then what kind of... like one person was supposed to eat it,
we just don't know which one. Right. Yeah, but this is a
case where it's not חבורה chabura as one person. But it's no
better than when they got mixed up before שחיטה, shechita, the same...
it's the same scenario repeated. Okay, הי מאי, Hei mai, what should
you say? ליתי כל חד מינייהו פסחא Leiti kol chad mineihu pascha
ויתני ויאמר, ve'itni veyomar, maybe everybody should bring their own individual פסח
שני Pesach Sheni and make a stipulation. אי דידי הוה בעל מום,
I didi hava ba'al mum, if mine was the one with blemish,
האי דאייתי השתא ליהוי פסח, hai de'aiti hashta lihavei pesach, this is
my פסח. Pesach. אי דידי תם הוה, I didi tam hava, if
mine was the good one, האי דאייתי השתא ליהוי שלמים, hai de'aiti
hashta lihavei shelamim, let it be a שלמים. shelamim. That's a great
solution. Okay, he does a פסח Pesach or it's a שלמים. shelamim.
Let everybody bring it on the second פסח. Pesach. No, לא אפשר,
lo efshar, no you can't do that, משום דאיכא חזה ושוק דכהנים
דאכלי ליה. mishum de'ika chaze veshok dekahaneim de'achli lei. No, cause if
it's a שלמים shelamim you have to give the כהן kohen the
חזה chaze and the שוק, shok, the breast and the thigh, and
since the כהן kohen is... and which you wouldn't do by פסח
שני, Pesach Sheni, and if it turns out that it's a פסח
שני, Pesach Sheni, again you have the קרבן פסח korban Pesach being
eaten by somebody who is not part of the group of the
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. That's an interesting thing. Why not bring it
and you eat that and have nobody eat the חזה chaze and
שוק? shok? Okay, well you know what? The גמרא isn't done, so
we'll continue the conversation tomorrow.